Guide to the Richard Maass Collection of Westchester and New York State 1645-1995, (Bulk: 1645-1910) MSS.055
Fales Library and Special Collections
Richard Maass Westchester and New York State History Collection
1645-1995
1645-1910
Fales Library and Special Collections
Maass, Richard A.
MSS.055
12 Linear Feet (21 boxes)
Richard Maass, a Westchester County resident, NYU alumnus and highly successful investment banker, was active in the political and educational affairs of New York and Westchester (Mayor of White Plains in 1974 and Westchester County Historian, 1974-1981). Maass amassed this unique collection of historical documents over a fifty-year period. It contains more than three hundred items relating to the early history of New York State, with a particular focus on the American Revolutionary War.
Provenance
The Richard Maass Collection of Westchester and New York State was donated to the Fales Library by Mr. Maass in two installments during the fall and winter of 1996. An additional gift of materials about Charles Lee and Benedict Arnold was donated by Dolly Maass in the Fall of 1999. These materials have been processed and added to the collection as Series VI.
Access Restrictions
Repository permission is required for access. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biographical Note
Richard Maass was an alumnus of New York University, having graduated from the School of Commerce (now the Stern School) in 1949 with a degree in economics. Maass was active in the political and educational affairs of the county; he was appointed as mayor of White Plains in 1974, and held the office of Westchester County Historian from 1974 to 1981. Maass served his community as the President of the Purchase College Council, and was a member of the American Jewish Committee and the Westchester County Historical Society. Along with his father-in-law, Richard M. Lederer, who served for many years as the Village Historian for Scarsdale, Maass was involved with the Manuscript Society from its earliest inception, and served as president of the organization from 1954-1956. In addition to the collecting interests represented by the Richard Maass Collection of Westchester and New York State, Maass assembled notable collections of Abraham Lincoln and Thomas Paine materials, as well as a significant collection of books relating to pirates.
Scope and Content Note
The Richard Maass Collection of Westchester and New York State consists of over three hundred autograph letters, documents, and newspapers which chronicle the early history of New York State from its colonization by the Dutch to the mid-nineteenth century. The collection is, however, particularly rich in materials relating to the Revolutionary War and can provide researchers with multiple perspectives on significant events and individual military campaigns. For example, the Battle of White Plains is amply documented in the collection through correspondence from participants and observers, as well as in contemporary newspaper accounts.
The arrangement of the collection largely reflects Maass's own organization. Each manuscript, with a few exceptions, has been listed and described in the finding aid. For many of the items the collection also holds additional information provided by Maass regarding specific documents. These have been retained and, in Series I, II, III, IV, and VI, filed in folders designated with the letter "A" following the documents they describe. These folders are not listed in the finding but share the same number; for instance if one wishes to consult Maass' information regarding the materials in Series IA Box 1 Folder 1 one should request Series IA Box 1 Folder 1A. Almost every folder for each item in the collection contained a one to two page description of the document, as well as other ancillary materials such as transcriptions and/or translations of documents by Maass. These folders also occasionally contained provenance information and transcripts. Any additions to the collection will be processed as separate accretions.
In addition to autograph letters and historical documents, the Maass Collection contained a small amount of printed materials. These chiefly consisted of over thirty different early American, British, and French newspapers, dating mainly from the eighteenth century. These items have been organized as a separate series (Series V).
SERIES DESCRIPTION:
Series I: New York State
Series I contains documents pertaining to the history of New York State, exclusive of Westchester County, with a particular emphasis on New York City. It is arranged chronologically.
Subseries A contains two legal boxes of letters and documents dating from the early settlement of New York by the Dutch through the late eighteenth century. These documents range from records of everyday life in both the Dutch and British colonies to contemporary descriptions of significant historical and political events affecting the colonies and the new state. This subseries also contains numerous documents relating to the Revolutionary War in New York State, including an eyewitness account of the British invasion of New York City in 1776 by Mrs. A. Hampton.
Subseries B is the James Alexander Collection. It contains eight letters to and from Alexander (1691-1756) and his wife, Mary, housed in one small legal box. Alexander was surveyor-general of New York and New Jersey, an attorney, and a contributor to the New York Weekly Journal. In 1735 he was disbarred because he served as counsel for Journal editor Peter Zenger in the famous freedom-of-the-press case. Alexander also was a co-founder of the American Philosophical Society. The James Alexander Collection was purchased as a group by Mr. Maass.
Subseries C contains oversize material, mainly consisting of deeds and other records of land grants in New York City and State. It is housed in two flat boxes.
Series II. Westchester
Series II contains documents pertaining to the early history of what is present day Westchester County. It is arranged chronologically.
Subseries A contains a wide range of letters and other documents dating from the late seventeenth century to the middle of the nineteenth century, but the bulk of the material in this subseries dates from the Revolutionary War period. Included within the four legal boxes of this subseries are numerous receipts, orderly and pay books, and correspondence from military officers, including ten documents or letters from George Washington.
Subseries B contains oversize material, mainly consisting of deeds and other records of land grants inWestchester. These are housed in a flat box, with the exception of one item which is kept in the map case.
Series III: Mayors and Governors Autographs
Series III contains correspondence and other documents signed by mayors of New York City and Governors of New York State (and New Jersey). It is arranged chronologically.
Subseries A contains materials which represent the broadest range of dates in the collection. It begins with a document signed by the first Van Cortlandt, Oloff Stevenson, a burgomaster of New Amsterdam, and concludes with a check signed by William Gaynor, an early twentieth century mayor of New York City. The selection of governors is equally diverse, and includes two documents signed by the notorious Lord Cornbury (Edward Hyde) as well as the extremely rare autograph of George Clarke.
Subseries B contains oversize material signed by various mayors or governors. It is housed in a flat box, with the exception of one item which is kept in the map case.
Series IV: Other Historical Letters and Manuscripts
Series IV contains documents which do not relate directly to the history of New York State. It contains only three items in one small legal box, but among these are included a Massachusetts resolution signed by Samuel Warren, Samuel Adams, and John Hancock, and an important letter from John Quincy Adams regarding the abolition of slavery.
Series V: Printed Materials
Series V contains printed materials and Mr. Maass' notes relating to these items. The newspapers are divided by size into two groups, each of which is organized alphabetically by title.
Subseries A contains one legal box and two flat boxes of newspapers. Small-sized newspapers are arranged in alphabetical order in the legal box. A second alphabetical arrangement of larger-sized newspapers are housed in two flat boxes. Folders 55 through 62 contain manuscripts that were not assigned folder numbers during the original processing of the collection.
Subseries B contains three archival storage boxes, numbered 17, 18, and 19, holding research notes and transcriptions or translations of the various articles made by Mr. Maass. They have been sorted into separate folders which are arranged alphabetically and then chronologically. This subseries is not enumerated in the container list.
Series VI: Accretions
Subseries A contains letters to and from General Charles Lee.
Subseries B contains letters by and about Benedict Arnold and is especially rich in eyewitness accounts of the events and trials surrounding his failed collaboration with the British in 1781.
Arrangement
Folders are mainly arranged chronologically within each series.
The files are grouped into 6 series:
Missing Title
Series I. New York State
Series II. Westchester
Series III. Mayors and Governors Autographs
Series IV. Other Historical Letters and Manuscripts
Series V. Printed Materials
Series VI. Accretions
Separated Material
The following titles have been removed from the collection and catalogued in BobCat. Mr. Maass's notes and translations for these items are held in Series V subseries B, which is not described in the container list.
Annals of Annapolis: comprising sundry notices of that old city from the period of the first settlements in its vicinity in the year 1649, until the war of 1812.
La Gazette de France. (1775-1783)
The Lee papers, 1754-[1811]
Nouvelles extraordinaires de divers endroits. (1775-1776)
The treason of Charles Lee: major general second in command in the American Army of the Revolution.
Pamphlets.; Autographs (manuscripts).; Newspapers.; New York (State); Correspondence.; Book collectors.; Book collecting.; New York (N.Y.) |x History |y Revolution, 1775-1783.; New York (N.Y.) |x History |y Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; Westchester County (N.Y.) |x History.; Westchester County (N.Y.) |x Politics and government.; Wills; Muster rolls.; Clippings (information artifacts); Governors |z New York (State).; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; United States |x History |y Revolution, 1775-1783 |v Periodicals.; United States |x History |x Revolution, 1773-1783 |v Personal narratives.; New York (State) |x History |y 1775-1865.; Bedford (Westchester County, N.Y.) |x History |y Battle of, 1779.; Long Island, Battle of, New York, N.Y., 1776.; Westchester County (N.Y.) |x History |x Revolution, 1775-1783.; Westchester County (N. Y.) |x History |v Periodicals.; Westchester County (N.Y.) |x History |x Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; Broadsides (notices); Autographs |z United States |x Collections.; United States |x History |x Revolution,1773-1783 |x American forces.; United States |x History |x Revolution,1775-1783 |x Regimental histories.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Public officers |z New York (State); Wyllys, George, 1710-1796; Washington, George, 1732-1799; Wood, Fernando, 1812-1881; Varick, Richard, 1753-1831; Wadsworth, Jeremiah, 1743-1804; Stuyvesant, Peter, 1592-1672; Van Cortlandt, Stephanus, 1642-1700; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848; Arnold, Benedict, 1741-1801; Biddle, Clement, 1740-1814; Burnet, William, 1688-1729; Clinton, Henry, Sir, 1738?-1795; Clinton, George, 1739-1812; Colden, Cadwallader, 1688-1776; De Peyster, Abraham, d. 1768?; Dunmore, John Murray, Earl of, 1732-1809; Ellsworth, Oliver, 1745-1807; Gates, Horatio, 1728-1806; Greene, Nathanael, 1742-1786; Heath, William, 1737-1814; Hewitt, Abram S. (Abram Stevens), 1822-1903; Clarendon, Edward Hyde, Earl of, 1661-1723; Hunter, Robert, 1666-1734; Jay, John, 1745-1829; Irving, Washington, 1783-1859; Lee, Charles, 1731-1782; Kieft, Wilhelm, ca. 1600-1647; Livingston, Robert, 1654-1728; Livingston, Philip, 1716-1778; Morris, Lewis, 1671-1746; Parsons, Samuel Holden, 1737-1789; Nicolls, Richard, 1624-1672; Radcliff, Jacob, 1764-1844; Putnam, Israel, 1718-1790; Sheldon, Elisha, 1740-1805; Reed, Joseph, 1741-1785
- Series I: New York State
  Scope and Content note
  Series I contains documents pertaining to the history of New York State, exclusive of Westchester County, with a particular emphasis on New York City. It is arranged chronologically.
  - Subseries A: Letters and Documents
    Series I: Subseries A contains two legal boxes of letters and documents dating from the early settlement of New York by the Dutch through the late eighteenth century. These documents range from records of everyday life in both the Dutch and British colonies to contemporary descriptions of significant historical and political events affecting the colonies and the new state. This subseries also contains numerous documents relating to the Revolutionary War in New York State, including an eyewitness account of the British invasion of New York City in 1776 by Mrs. A. Hampton.
    - creator: Kiefft, Willem. place: [New Amsterdam], Oct 19, 1645; 055-001-a-0001; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General Physical Description
      physical description: Parchment, (Plus 3 fragments); d.s.
      extent:
      dimensions: 21cm x 20cm
      Abstract
      Land deed granting Byleveldt's bouwery to Leendert Arenden (or Arentsen). Signed by Kiefft.
    - creator: Loockermans, Govert. place: Midwout, New Netherland, Aug 7, 1654; 055-001-a-0002; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 2)
      physical description: single half sheet; d.s.
      dimensions: 32cm x 22cm
      1657 copy of an agreement regarding the sale of goats by Loockermans to John Hathaway. Signed by Hathaway and Loockermans, notarized by Matheus De Vos (1657).
    - creator: Jansz, S. Marten. place: New Amsterdam, Sep 28, 1654; 055-001-a-0003; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 3)
      physical description: quarter sheet; d.s.
      dimensions: 22cm x 19cm
      Court Messenger summons two wives for a hearing. Signed by Marten Jansz, attorney for Henrick Cornelisz.
    - creator: Hathaway, John. place: Amersvoort, New Netherland, Mar 31, 1655; 055-001-a-0004; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
      dimensions: 22cm x 32 cm
      1657 copy of a deed of sale of land by John Hathaway to Govert Loockermans. Signed by Hathaway and Loockermans, witnessed by Elbert Elbertsen and Johannes Van Brugh, notarized by Matheus de Vos (1657).
    - creator: Hudde, Andries. place: [New Amsterdam], Apr 29, 1655; 055-001-a-0007; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 5)
      physical description: folded single sheet; d.s.
      dimensions: 39cm x 31cm
      Copy of a deed of sale for land at Amersfort by Hudde to Marten Jans. Witnessed by Hendrick Van Dyck and Jan Jansen, notarized by Dirck Van Schelluyne.
    - creator: De Meyer, Nicholas. place: [New Amsterdam], Aug 26, 1662; 055-001-a-0010; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 6)
      dimensions: 21cm x 33cm
      Sale of goods by De Meyer to Roelof Martensen Schenck (Roelof Martens). Notarized by Salomon Lachaire.
    - creator: Florisz, Claes. place: Amsterdam, Jun 26, 1663; 055-001-a-0013; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 7)
      physical description: one third of half sheet; d.s.
      dimensions: 23cm x 12cm
      Port clearance for the ship Star from Amsterdam to New Amsterdam. Signed by Florisz.
    - creator: Van Curler, Jacob. place: Gravesend, Jun 9, 1667; 055-001-a-0014; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 8)
      physical description: one third of half sheet; a. d.s.
      dimensions: 22cm x 13cm
      Confirmation of a sale of property, known as Bouwery no. 17 to Willem Beekman. Signed by Van Curler.
    - creator: Cockinga, Scato. place: The Hague, Mar 24, 1674; 055-001-a-0017; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 9)
      physical description: single half sheet; l. s.
      dimensions: 19cm x 30cm
      Concerning Dutch interests on Manhattan, from the States General to the Admiralty of Zeeland. Signed by Cockinga and countersigned by H. Fagel.
    - creator: Livingston, Robert, 1654-1728 place: [New York], [Oct 11,] 1682; 055-001-a-0018; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 10)
      physical description: single half sheet; a. d.s.
      Transmission of a message from the Mohawks (Maquase).
    - creator: Santen, Lucas. place: New York, Nov 25, 1686; 055-001-a-0019; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 11)
      physical description: folded single sheet, address overleaf; a. d.s.
      dimensions: 47cm x 36cm
      A complaint to the king against Governor Dongan.
    - creator: Will of Christina Cappoens place: New York, Jun 17, 1687; 055-001-a-0022; 11 pages (Box 1, Folder 12)
      physical description: 4 sheets quired and stitched. -A1 and A2; a. d.s.
      no note
    - creator: Addington, Isaac, 1645-1715. place: Boston, Apr 15, 1691; 055-001-a-0034; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 13)
      physical description: folded single half sheet, with address overleaf and seal; a.l.s.
      dimensions: 36cm x 24cm
      To John Clarkson.
    - creator: Colony of New York place: [London], [1698]; 055-001-a-0035; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 14)
      dimensions: 19cm x 31cm
      Abstract of money placed for expeditions to Albany, etc. in the accompts of Mr. Chisley Brooke.
    - creator: Colony of New York place: [London], [1702]; 055-001-a-0038; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 14)
      dimensions: 19cm x 29cm
      Abstract of money placed for Lord Cornbury's expedition to Albany, etc. Docketed in the hand of William Blathwayt on the verso.
    - creator: Colony of New York place: [London], [1705]; 055-001-a-0039; 4 pages (Box 1, Folder 14)
      physical description: folded single sheet; a. d.s.
      dimensions: 37cm x 30 cm
      Audit of Governor Cornbury's accounts.
    - creator: De Peyster, Abraham, d.1768? place: New York, Aug 29, 1701; 055-001-a-0044; 4 pages (Box 1, Folder 15)
      physical description: folded full sheet; a.l.s.
      dimensions: 40cm x 32 cm
      To William Blathwayt
    - creator: Blathwayt, William, 1688-1704. place: New York, Jan 31, 1704; 055-001-a-0049; 9 pages (Box 1, Folder 16)
      physical description: three full sheets, quired; d.s.
      dimensions: 37cm x 30cm
      Report on plantation revenues.
    - creator: Hyde, Edward, Earl of Clarendon, 1661-1723. place: New York, Aug 28, 1704; 055-001-a-0059; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 17)
      physical description: Single half sheet; d.s.
      dimensions: 19cm x 25cm
      License granted to Richard Floyd to take 'drift whales' off the north shore of Long Island.
    - creator: List of New York Accompts of the Revenue. place: London, 1705; 055-001-a-0060; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 18)
      physical description: folded full sheet; a. d.s.
      dimensions: 37cm x 31cm
      Docketed by William Blathwayt.
    - creator: Livingston, John. place: New York, Jul 20, 1710; 055-001-a-0061; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 19)
      physical description: folded full sheet; d.s.
      dimensions: 41cm x 33cm
      Petition to Governor Robert Hunter regarding the estate of Livingston's father-in-law, John Winthrop.
    - creator: Livingston, Robert, 1654-1728. place: Albany, Jul 11, 1720; 055-001-a-0064; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 20)
      physical description: folded full sheet, address overleaf with seal; l. s.
      dimensions: 43cm x 33cm
      Warning that the French are 'debauching' the Five Nations. Signed by Livingston, Johannes Cuyler, John Riggs, John Schuyler, and Myndert Schuyler.
    - creator: Walter, Robert. place: New York, Apr 18, 1721; 055-001-a-0065; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 21)
      physical description: folded full sheet, quired half sheet (21cm x 31cm); d.s.
      dimensions: 43cm x 32cm
      Notice to Sherrif to summon a grand jury. Signed by Walter, John Cruger, Frederick Philipse, Jacob Kip, and Hermanus Vangelder.
    - creator: Livingston, Philip, 1686-1749. place: Albany, Sep 6, 1721; 055-001-a-0066; 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 22)
      dimensions: 42cm x 33cm
      Lease of house and land to Johannes Kessler. Signed by Livingston, John De Peyster, Myndert Schuyler, Peter Van Brugh, Robert Livingston, Jr. and John Schuyler.
    - creator: Van Rensselaer, Hendrick. place: Albany, Jun 5, 1735; 055-001-a-0070; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 23)
      physical description: single half sheet, address overleaf; d.s.
      Bond from John Lindesay and Peter Winne for debts owed. Witnessed by Van Rensselaer and Gilbert Livingston. Docketed.
    - creator: Morris, Lewis, 1671-1746. place: [New Jersey], Feb 8, 1739; 055-001-a-0071; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 24)
      dimensions: 22cm x 33cm
      Petition for a hearing regarding a complaint the defendants had ignored previously. Signed by Lewis Morris.
    - creator: Johnson, William, Sir, 1715-1774. place: [New York], Dec 17, 1755; 055-001-a-0074; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 25)
      physical description: folded single half sheet; l. s.
      dimensions: 25cm x 38cm
      To Governor Morris (?) regarding the behavior of Indians of the Shawanese, Delaware, and the Six Nations.
    - creator: Loudon, John Campbell, Earl of place: Whitehall, Mar 11, 1756; 055-001-a-0075; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 26)
      physical description: folded full sheet, with address overleaf; a.l.s.
      To Major General Sir William Johnson
    - creator: Livingston, Peter Van Brugh. place: New York, Sep 9, 1765; 055-001-a-0078; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 27)
      physical description: single half sheet; a.l.s.
      dimensions: 21cm x 30cm
      To John S. Lawrence.
    - creator: Colden, Cadwalader, 1688-1776. place: New York, Nov 5, 1765; 055-001-a-0079; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 28)
      physical description: quarter sheet, badly damaged; a.l.s.
      dimensions: 19cm x 23cm
      To the Marquis of Granby, regarding New York riots over the Stamp Act.
    - creator: Fanning, David. place: s.l., Dec 7, 1773; 055-001-a-0082; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 29)
      physical description: fragment of half sheet; d.s.
      dimensions: 19cm x 14cm
      To Benadom Gallup. Charges Cathron Eldriedg of Groton with fornication and bearing an illegitimate child. Signed by Fanning and witnessed by Desiah Burros and Mary Eldriedg.
    - creator: Colden, Cadwalader, 1688-1776. place: New York, Jul 19, 1774; 055-001-a-0083; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 30)
      dimensions: 20cm x 13cm
      Sight draft drawn on Nathaniel Coffin at Boston. Signed by Colden.
    - creator: Beekman, William place: [New Amsterdam], undated; 055-001-c-0204; 1 pages (Box 1, Folder 31)
      physical description: fragment of sheet, had been mounted and framed with caption and map of lower Manhattan (See Series I subseries C Box 4 Folder 1); a. d.s.
      dimensions: 19cm x 11cm
      Request for mortgage. For an english translation and information regarding William Beekman see Series I subseries C box 4 folder 1.
    - creator: Pay list for Captain Varick's troops. place: Albany, Jul 5, 1776; 055-001-a-0084; 2 pages (Box 2, Folder 32)
      physical description: single half sheet (sliced in half, repair?); a. d.s.
      dimensions: 23cm x 37 cm
    - creator: Howe, Richard Howe, Earl, 1726-1799. place: On Board H. M. S. Eagle off Staten Island, Jul 15, 1776; 055-001-a-0087; 6 pages (Box 2, Folder 33)
      physical description: two full sheets, quired and stitched; a. d.s.
      To Captain Henry.
    - creator: Varick, Richard, 1753-1831. place: Albany, Jul 29, 1776; 055-001-a-0094; 1 pages (Box 2, Folder 34)
      To Capt. Bacon, Mentions Benedict Arnold
    - creator: Tory document. place: Hartford, Jul 29, 1776; 055-001-a-0095; 1 pages (Box 2, Folder 35)
      physical description: fragment of half sheet; a. d.s.